Okay, so in this lesson, we're going to be diving into how TypeScript handles function
parameters and return types.
So functions are the heart of our logic and TypeScript, of course, helps us make sure that
they behave exactly as expected.
So we're going to learn how to annotate inputs, control outputs, and catch bugs before
they happen.
So why type our functions?
Typing functions is going to give us three big wins.
First, the clarity, so we know exactly what goes in and what comes out of our functions.
Secondly, safety, because TypeScript's going to catch our mismatches before we discover
things in runtime.
And thirdly, tooling, because we're going to get better autocomplete, refactoring, and
also documentation.
So let's have a look at a very basic function, so we're going to do function, and perhaps
just do a simple greet function, and we want to give or supply a person's name.
So we can just do name, and just like normally, we can do a colon, and then supply the
type, so in this case string, and then, so if we want to specify the return type of the
function, we can then do another colon, and then we specify the return type.
So in this case, we want to turn a type of string.
Now we can define our function in a normal way with some curly braces, and of course TypeScript
is already complaining, because we haven't actually defined or returned a simple string.
So let's now do return, and just do back ticks, hello, and perhaps dollar, and then
name, and then a colon, and that seems to do that.
So of course we're going to get our TypeScript is going to be one happy puppy.
In addition to explicitly specifying the return type for our function, TypeScript, just
like I've already mentioned earlier in the course, can also infer the type from our
return type.
So let's do another function here, and let's say we have a function of the double, and
we want to supply number, and we've got curly bother to give it the return type, but
we can let TypeScript figure it out.
So if we do return, and then say x multiplied by 2, then TypeScript is going to be able
to figure out, as you can see here, that this is returning a number.
But generally it's not great practice to not actually specify the type, because that's
kind of the whole point of TypeScript, otherwise we're falling back into the JavaScript
world, so it's always helpful to annotate them explicitly, especially in things like public
APIs or when doing complex logic.
Now let's move on and have a look at another feature, which is optional and default parameters
in TypeScript.
Now we can do this, I'm not going to clear this screen here, let's say we have a function,
and we have a log function, and we want to supply a message of type string, and perhaps
we also want to supply a level of type string, we want to default this second parameter
to an actual type of string, so if we don't, we can't be bothered to supply it, then it's
going to fill it in for us.
We could do that by doing an equal sign, and then specify in the actual string, so let's
say we want to set it to info, then we can start to find our function, we can just do
anything we want here, like console log, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, and then to find
and just output the message in a normal way.
And of course, when we actually come to call the function, we would just do log to supply
a message, perhaps like service started, and if we can't be bothered to, then actually
output or supply the string, then of course it's going to be supplied for us, but we could
also then override it and do like server crashed, and then we can actually give it a type,
or us another string, and say for example error, and it's then obviously going to override
the value that we have set as a default here, so that's if we want to do some default
parameters, but what about optional parameters?
Now for that, let's just do another quick example here, so I'm going to call up a function,
let's say greet, and let's just say we can't be bothered to actually supply the name, so
what we can do is we can give it a question mark, and then the type, so this then becomes
an optional parameter, that allows us to do something like double check that it's been actually
being passed in, and if it is, then we just do our sort of hello message and supply the
person's name, name, whatever it is, otherwise we can just say hello, a guest, or something
like this.
Now one thing to also bear in mind is you could also to find reusable function shapes
using what we've already seen before, which is the aliases, now as a kind of reminder of this,
we could for example have a really complex map operation, it's going to be so complex we're
going to just literally supply two things, in A and B as a number, and we can then say
that this returns a type of number, and then we can actually define a natural function
like this and say multiply, the multiply is going to take these two numbers, and then it's
going to return this number, we then say it's a mathematical operation, or type of mathematical
operation, of which we then supply the x and y parameters, and then we can define the
actual function or the implementation of that type, so for the case of multiply we might
do x times y, and then we can do for example carry on, let's say we want to do have an
add function, we would then do an add, use of type, or use in a type alias of math up,
we then also supply the x and y number, and then we define that implementation, let's
say x plus y, and we can do one more, let's say for example divide, and of course you
can see what's going to happen here is we have a math up, we can type correctly, we
supply the x and the y, and then we define the implementation for the function x divided
by y, now you can see hopefully you can see how this can become quite useful if you have
a number of different operations, rather than having to keep on typing this every single
time you define the function, you can just refer to that shape of the function and using
this syntax here, functions don't necessarily have to only return one thing, we can also
return multiple things, so let's say for example we have a function here, and called
pass input, we supply an input of type string, now this pass we could maybe want to return
a number, or you want to return, let's say a no value, so you can say it returns a number
or it returns a no value, then we define our function, let's say we do an implementation
such as pass, equals a number, inputs, and then if that is not a number, using standard
none, is none of our past, then we just return a no, otherwise we return the number, and
that then is satisfied, satisfies type scripts that we're supplying over the number, or
the actual no value, so not just variables can actually be our union type, we can also
to find a union's hype on this function.